so what would you say if somebody asked
you how to be mindful how to sustain your
how to be mindful how to sustain your
mindfulness
how to carry on being mindful not like
you must be mindful then you're mindful
when you remember to be mindful
but then you lapse you forget so how
would you i was how to sustain
mindfulness
well if you know what mindfulness is
then you can sustain it
yeah so already if you have a right
direction so what would then so how would you
so what would then so how would you
sustain it
how would you know what it is in order
to sustain it
well you need to know what you so you
have to be mindful of what mindful of
let's say for you of the body
okay so yeah so you need something to be
mindful of
so what would be difference between
being mindful of the body
and being mindful of this i don't know
roof above my head
being mindful of the body and being
mindful of my hands
what's the difference
the thing that you're placing it yeah
how specific or how general it is
the roof is not your i mean the roof but
you can i can be mindful of the roof if
i'm worried that something will fall on
the roof and destroy it so i am very
mindful of what's happening to the roof
yeah but that's the difference is like
whether it's a specific thing
or whether you're something that's more
like fundamental to your experience such
as your body your feeling
the whole um so i could be mine if i'm
doing work here
that and this this roof might fall down
yeah then i'm mindful of that roof
that context that whatever i'm doing
here is subject
to because you're on the roof but why
is then being mindful of your body
better than being mindful of the roof
why would that be better because there's
a different
goal well that only because it already
includes mindfulness of the roof see if
you're under the roof they might fall if
you're mindful of your body you're
already mindful of the danger of it
being crushed by the roof or anything
other than the roof
but if you're mindful of the roof
anything else that's higher than that
you won't be mindful of
so that's what least the mindfulness um
the points for the collection points for
mindfulness are the reference points but
it matters what
reference point so not like i'm mindful
of of pleasure that i'm chasing
yeah you're mindful of feeling but
that's a mindfulness feeling
don't be mindful of feeling in the
general sense that includes every other
particular feeling you might be going
through so mindful of the nature that you're
so mindful of the nature that you're
subjected to feeling
oh yeah mindful of the body is there
regardless of whether it's the risk of
this or something else
because that reveals then the whole
scope of what that body is subjected to
not just the particular danger of the
roof and the non-danger if you step outside
and the non-danger if you step outside
of the possibly imminently falling roof
so whatever you're doing you're mindful
of that context
yeah that's where we always kind of
randomly volunteer you are already in
the your body already gives you the provides
your body already gives you the provides
you the basis for the context you're in
so just not forgetting not
yeah so how would you then not forget
that's how you sustain
because you would still lapse so you
want to basically say why you lapse
and how not to lapse from the context
that is there so when you labs from your
mindfulness you have a lapse from the body that's
you have a lapse from the body that's
subjected to all these things
so you then you can't change the body
and what's subjected to
so then it's only because of stuff you
do that you get to lapse from what's
obvious so remembering the context you're asking
so remembering the context you're asking
how to remember
and then refraining from doing things
that basically are contradicting the
context that they're countering they're
against it
the context of that like oh this body is
subjected to this whole vast
scope domain of things that i cannot
even fathom and you feel that
but then if you ignore it and it's our
roof is the danger i avoid the roof thus
i am safe
and you ignore the fact that that's only
a relative safety
a relative sort of ease but if you
kind of reconnect with the notion here
but the body is still there depends on
the organs depends on the elements
so there's no safety there but that's
unpleasant now
so i don't want to play this pleasure so
i'll just selectively kind of pick on
and establish my mind upon safety
relative safety
so that's why you lapse from mindfulness
because you choose to ignore the context
because it's unpleasant at times
not always but at times it's unpleasant
and you you don't want it
so you want to sustain the mindfulness
stop trying to avoid displeasure
pretty much of any kind not torture
yourself but when
unpleasant feeling manifest stop trying
to justify it outrun it
explain it get rid of it you have to
allow it to endure
and by the way that's another way you
could easily be mindful effortlessly
be mindful of the context find something
deeply concerning
because the whole life revolves around
avoiding concerns
covering them up dealing with them
literally
so there's always a concern in the back
of your mind
but that's obviously a bit edgy because
it can overwhelm you
so finding a concern yeah something so
i'm concerned of losing something find
that and then work through that
something might change
and you don't need to see like when
there is a concern present your
experience the effort is not never is on the level
the effort is not never is on the level
of
i need to keep this concern otherwise
i'll forget about it
no the effort is i must forget about
this i must outrun it
so if you find a concern you will be
unable to forget about it
unless you unless you intentionally make
this excess effort to cover it up
so remember what you're concerned yeah
so like basically dig up the concern or
as the buddha would say sense of urgency
and that will effortlessly stay there
you don't need effort because if you
just take mindfulness on your own terms
i'm mindful now
you need all this effort to keep that
mindfulness going because this is going
to fade because it's not really the
mindfulness mindfulness it's not based
on the context you're in
it's the context that you kind of
scraped up thinking that's what the
context i mean
but if you find a concern you'll never
intentionally scrape up the concern and
enjoy it to be there
so what's concerning about the body is
you don't even need to start
specifically about concern of the body
just any concern any knees that you have
any concern any knees that you have
and then sit exactly allow that thought
to endure you are mindful of the body
there you're mindful of the feeling there
you're mindful of the feeling there
you're mindful of the danger
well it becomes very apparent yeah so
as i said that the only effort then you
would be making would not be effort i
must stay mindful because you are
mindful because the concern will endure
effortlessly the only effort you will be making and
the only effort you will be making and
thus restraining yourself from making it
if you want to practice mindfulness is
effort for distracting yourself from
that concerned mindfulness
and that's easier it's clear often
like as you said you can't be mindful
because you know what mindfulness is and
now you know exactly what will take you
away from this concern and you choose to not
from this concern and you choose to not
do it because then you will lose your
mindfulness so that little recognition of i am pray
so that little recognition of i am pray
to suffering
and you cannot shake it off because it's
literally that's your situation it's
unshakable the only the
way people can shake it off is cover it
up which we don't shake it off they just
put a bandage on the wound so they don't
not treat the wound but not to see the
wound so just make up so you don't see that
so just make up so you don't see that
the wounds still very much there
it doesn't need to be some great concern
that you cannot possibly cope with
but you certainly need to start digging
them up because they are there
most people's lives revolve around
avoiding anxiety
and trying to basically prevent it from
arising yet
if your situation is not already deeply
anxious as a human being you wouldn't be
as a human being you wouldn't be
experiencing anxiety to begin with
it's just a revelation of what your
situation already is
and that kind of breeds their whole kind
of dependence on sensuality and the
whole constant movement constant
activity constant projects
because if i stop i settle back into my
situation and that's already the
beginning of mindfulness
so you realize most people lose
mindfulness it's because deep down they
don't want to be mindful
they want to do mindfulness on their own
terms but they don't want to be mindful
because that reveals this
oh the nature of my situation that's
subject to change subject to all these
things that are beyond that's
frightening frightening from the point
of view of my assumed change in control
not fighting in itself if you get used
to the fear will go away
it's a right concern yeah we actually
spoke about them yeah we did
now the whole talk on the right concerns
like the what prerequisites yeah yeah
that's it there it is
concern i didn't have any mind we
started but that's exactly what it is
yeah the right concern will result in it
so right concern right mindfulness right
mindfulness right concern
and right mindfulness as the buddha said
it's where you can't have too much of it
you can't overdo your situation you can
just be more
clearer and clearer about it and if
you're clear about
to the extent necessary you will uh have
uprooted any misconstrued notions and assumptions
any misconstrued notions and assumptions
about the nature of what you're
subjected to the nature of a nature
nature of change that whole thing
the only reason you carry on these
gratuitous assumptions and sense of
ownership and my and i am
is because you you really like you
maintain it
through refusing to address the basic
characteristics of your situation so
so if if i just say uh be mindful of the
body without seeing it having no concern
without seeing it having no concern
over it yeah it's gonna be mechanical
it's gonna be kind of poor
yeah boring it might be difficult and
that's exactly why you won't be able to
sustain it that's exactly any
more no no that's not mindfulness of the
body that's mindfulness or what you
assume about it to be
that's what i mean like if you do
mindfulness rightly you it's not it's
not you're doing
it's just discerning what's already
there that's exactly why mindfulness
results in combination of knowledge
literally of understanding you have to
see the danger in the body
so you have that see seeing the danger
of the body is actually
more aligned with mindfulness of the
body then you be mindful of the body
yeah when you do that oh i'm mindful of
the body now you know i'm feeling this
chair because once you grasp the danger that's
because once you grasp the danger that's
already you're not gonna
be you can have one eye open oh yes
people you're already alert
yeah you're going to be alert hateful so
people want to be alert and hateful on
their own terms
without feeling the pain of that anxiety
and danger
and that's then not alertness isn't it
yeah left to one so then no but i'm like
this is still alertness i maintain the
view that this is still mindfulness of
the body
i just refuse to feel that concern on
account of it because it's unpleasant so
then you realize
even your committed practice of
mindfulness and alertness
is for the purpose of avoiding the
actual mindfulness and alertness
because it's unpleasant
and the only reason by the way that it
stays unpleasant
is you keep trying to avoid the
unavoidable if you accept it it ceases to be
if you accept it it ceases to be
unpleasant it becomes the norm
so having right concern you see the
danger so you're always thinking you're
always faced with this danger danger
danger the elements and evidence are
dangerous the body's dangerous
it's going to kill you and that
can seem like it would be overwhelming
but that's actually
the mindfulness but you think oh if i if
i'm constantly under this
threat i'm constantly threatened if
that's going to be overwhelming it's
going to send me
into madness you know it could yeah
trauma hence you want to have developed your
hence you want to have developed your
behavior beforehand and
keep it keep it in check sila virtue
sense restraint see your madness is not
measured even when people go mad you don't go mad
even when people go mad you don't go mad
by
what sort of pressuring you and what
type of things are making you like feel
this or that
you're mad by what type of action you do
in account or about pressuring
that's the definition of your madness
yeah i have these thoughts but i don't
act out of thoughts thus i'm not a mad
person but i had thoughts and i choose to do
but i had thoughts and i choose to do
these horrible things on account of
these thoughts
oh now yeah i'm a mad person because
look what he's done he's mad
so it doesn't matter how much they
pressure you your behavior is that which
makes you mad and
by the way even the suitors when that
when those monks were contemplating the
disgust of the body and death
and so on and then wanted to die so they
convinced that man to kill them because
he'll be getting lots of merit
everything got a bit skewed and that man
first didn't want to do it
he was concerned and once he killed the
first monk
he basically once he committed and gave
into that action
of what was pressuring him he went mad
and then went and started killing the
monks that didn't want to be killed
he said who else wants this nibana i'll
help him with this knife and then just
start hacking people
but not until he gave in to that so
although he obviously they saw i'll ask
him he might do it
like monks that did ask him so that he
might actually want to do it
so he was kind of giving off that vibe
but he didn't do it before
and he didn't want to do it first until
they kind of laid into him and convinced
him and praised the virtue of death
that's the peragic appraising virtue of
death to others
to make them kill them and then he did
and then he was like let loose danny was
just killing everybody
so he went mad after he said yes to
these mad actions
but if he was certain thoughts well not
said yes to mad thoughts but any
basically chosen to perform that actions
like even saying yes to mad thoughts
it's still not you doing the mad actions
but yeah it's obviously a necessary
basis for you than acting out
but if he was developed in virtue sense
restrained precepts he wouldn't he would have not
precepts he wouldn't he would have not
be able to do it
because the behavior of not doing it has
been basically hammered in and trained
sufficiently before so no amount of
pressure would have made him do it but he
would have made him do it but he
obviously wasn't developed in virtue
and then exposed to that level of
pressure and then he exploded
and that's exactly that if you start
contemplating dhamma on any kind by the
way the buddha said it's like a acoustic
the buddha said it's like a acoustic
grass if you grasp it wrongly it's going
to cut you open
it's like a snake if you don't catch it
right it will kill you literally the
dharma will kill you
because you will not be ready for it so
mindfulness of the body
will kill you unless you have been
developed in seal beforehand as it will
make you go mad
not specifically mindfulness of the body
and then some other no
mindfulness in itself because it reveals
the nature of human situation affected
with ignorance
with the whole burden of danger the
peril yeah
and the buddha said that there are only
two outcomes for a person who recognizes
that suffering
uh noble search as in okay this must be
dealt with
or mental derangement not third option
if you're threatened constantly buy
something every day in your face what like you try
every day in your face what like you try
and threaten a dog or something every
day what's going to happen to the dog well
what's going to happen to the dog well
yeah exactly it's going to try to get
away yeah or it's going to lose its mind
oh it's going to
go and when people think yeah but i'm
neither you know like yeah i think i have
you know like yeah i think i have
anxiety but see i don't need to become a
monk or practice the dhamma
and i'm not deranged means you're still
having lots of cover up
you're not really well it's a form of
engagement sure but
means basically oh you're not fully
admitting the nature of your situation
because if you do as the buddha said
there are only two
possible outcomes i will have to
practice the dharma and address this or
i'll go mad
there is no third option there so if
you're neither it's because you haven't
really came back to that source
that is your situation that is gonna
bite you but then it will be too late to
deal with it
so then if you are worried that you
might go mad that's a legitimate concern
or kind of practice in the dharma
committedly and you address it
not by not practicing the dhamma you
address it by
doubling down on the proper precepts
sense restraint
and strengthening yourself because that
is in your control always
what you choose to say yes or no to your
senses it's always on you
it's always your responsibility that was
that that
was kind of a funny thing but it's like
even when people go mad
and do crazy things on account of that
internal pressure of their thoughts
and then like try to put the reason for
their actions on their thoughts like oh
well i had thoughts i kind of i couldn't
resist it
and then this guy pointed out like how
come you never do good things on account
of those thoughts like oh these voices
told me to get a degree
yeah or these voices told me to go and
do charity it's always do bad things
like because that's basically what you
keep leaning on that's where the minds
lean mind affected with ignorance
greed aversion delusion leans in the
direction so whenever you engage in
avoiding responsibilities because you
want to cover up the bad things
so when you say i did that because of
the the thoughts no
you did that because you chose to do
these things but now you cannot accept
responsibility for it so you say it's
because of the thoughts
but when you do good things on account
of your thoughts oh that's always on you
that's right you
you don't say oh no it wasn't me who did
the charity i just had this random
impulse i wasn't in control i don't know what i
i wasn't in control i don't know what i
did basically no no
you calculate and you accept it and you
do it now that's good but you want to do
it
both ways as in take responsibility and
become aware of your situation
which will make sense restraint easier
then you realize okay
i can't control these things directly
what thoughts present themselves
to me but i can certainly control how
much i'm pressured by them
by basically controlling my actions they
would make that worse or better
nonsense restraint or sense restraint
containing myself like if you have no
container and you release the pressure
or the container is weak with cracks it
will explode
so dhamma practice of dharma is practice
of releasing the pressure
and it's not optional by the way the
pressure will be released sooner or
later against your will
so then what you do you prepare a
container that can contain the pressure
so it can be released so you can get the
the final basically combination of the
final product
pressurized sensory strain virtue
pressurized dharma
product parametric enlightenment
retirement the diamond yeah
i didn't say that it's used so many
times but yeah the diamond
it's a right concern again
seeing the danger seeing the threat
that's all evolving on the right concern
that's automatically
you're not going to be forgetting about
it
exactly exactly you're going to get
stabbed any moment the only reason you
forget about things is because you
haven't taken them on the right level
or could you intentionally distracted
yourself from it
if you take things on the right level
where the concern is
all you need to do then is abstain from
distracting yourself that's all you
so you don't really need to do anything
to maintain the mindfulness you just
need to kind of
um negatively sort of as in abstain from
certain actions and you will be
protecting it automatically
so if i want to stay dry and if i don't
need to keep myself dry all i need to do
is not keep jumping back in the water
much easier to do that than to keep
yourself dry if you're constantly wet
don't do anything that covers up exactly
don't do anything they will basically
cover up distract you from
the obviousness of that danger and by
the way that's that's
that's like the chief reason why people
do things
to distract themselves from there isn't
discomfort that's where you go after sensuality
that's where you go after sensuality
ownership craving
that's basically that's the craving in
the nutshell so see by practicing with
the right concern
kind of forcing yourself to be rightly
mindful you are fading away your craving
more or less you are not providing a
basis for maintenance of craving
because what is craving for pleasure
other than trying to avoid
this discomfort of not enough pleasure
like i want this means i don't have it
means that's uncomfortable
i cover up the discomfort by seeking on
that which will cover it up pleasure
what is craving in terms of the
discomfort when you want to get rid of
it other than trying to replace that
discomfort with something that's less
uncomfortable so again you're refusing to face the
so again you're refusing to face the
discomfort that's there
and seeking out to cover it up
and that's the principle of losing
mindfulness
and the reason why people will want to
practice mindfulness on their own terms
not in the terms of concern is because
then it's already just playing into that
already existing cover-up
oh my own terms means i don't really
need to rekindle or
open up this concern i can just pretend
i'm practicing mindfulness
like i can pretend i'm applying medicine
on top of a wound that i covered up
basically with with bandages and stuff
and haven't really addressed the
bacterial infection
but here i am now putting the cream on
top of the bandages
because if i open the bandages even too
unpleasant although i know in order for clean to
although i know in order for clean to
work i need to open up the bandages
if you're not seeing a threat you're
covering it up
yeah so and then even if you spend your
life doing the dhamma you're not
practicing the dharma
and that's the difference between you
doing or between discerning the concern
which doesn't need to be done
and just stays there everything's fine
everything's fine yeah it's fine
what i'll do later well you know i don't
know how i'm practicing but i'm sure i
am somehow
and i will have to bear the results of
it in the future like yeah but do you
know that that's practice right here
right now
do you know to what extent your your
effort is actually effort that that's
applying to the right things
or you just refuse to question it
so how to be mindful is to
be able to see the the threat of of
your body you can see the threat see the
situation which is dangerous
and which is dukkha see that you are
prey to suffering regardless of the
circumstances even if you are living in a palace
even if you are living in a palace
sheltered by
thousands of army so it's the knowledge
that you have
you get to see the knowledge well
mindfulness results in knowledge
it's a recognition of your situation
that's what mindfulness is
that's because too much of it as i said
and that's why if you stick to it
knowledge of your situation will have to
arise the certain the characteristic the
obviousness the nature becomes apparent not i have
the nature becomes apparent not i have
concocted the nature through my
theoretical reasoning
no the nature will become apparent known
discerned evident because you stop
covering it up
through mindfulness
and you will stop coding it up if you
stop expecting
or if you stop basically feeling
entitled internally
to avoiding discomfort to avoiding
anxiety
now you don't say you need to seek it
out like a maniac
so you certainly must not have the
attitude of this must be avoided at all
cost means practice of dharma must be avoided
means practice of dharma must be avoided
at all costs that's what you're saying
inadvertently
so being concerned about your feeling
feelings yeah being concerned for example about
yeah being concerned for example about
uh the fact you're subjected to feeling
good or bad and that it will have to
change as if the change is implicit in a
good feeling the change is implicit in a
bad feeling
are you not wanting that you wanting
good feeling on your own terms and you
wanting bad feeling on your own
as in wanting to go away wanting to come
here but if you see that it's already changed
but if you see that it's already changed
is implicit you wouldn't you would stop
resisting it
and that's literally the sort of
partners inside ah
change is implicit in this thing that's
here yeah so you wouldn't be so coming and
yeah so you wouldn't be so coming and
going is implicit in that change in that
pleasure like being mindful of the
pleasure means
yeah being mindful of the pleasure is
not necessarily pleasant
being mindful of the nature of the
pleasure can be very disconcerting yeah
that's right actually for example
being mindful of the pleasure of
sensuality is actually oh my goodness
it's like being mindful of holding a
deadly snake that you're not in control
of
but if you forget the deadliness of it
then you just or the other one even
better similarly the poisonous drink
so if you're mindful of the poison in
this beautifully smelling tasting
um consistency of this drink so poison
is undetectable
but you know it's in there so if you're
mindful of the poison of their drink
you'll be careful to not only spill it
on your skin let alone drink it
but if you basically forget that it's
poisonous oh you'll be
just chugging it down oh yeah you can't
have so i know what the where the poison is
so i know what the where the poison is
and enjoy with it let me enjoy the
pleasant part of it
because it will make that that's you
basically trying to kind of like practicing
trying to kind of like practicing
mindfulness on your own terms which is
not mindfulness and then trying to claim
that no no it's still on the right hand
it's still i still am aware of concern
and monks did that in the suttas when
they said in thermosensuality
uh when basically they thought that you
could be mindful of central danger and
engage with centrality at the same time
and the buddha said that's impossible
it's impossible to have central
perceptions of like
joy as delightful and at the same time
be mindful of basically
to have central perceptions not have
central perceptions as in
see this is dangerous and engage with
centrality so if you're engaging with sensuality
so if you're engaging with sensuality
means perceptions of sensuality has to
be there
meaning if you're engaging with
centrality not seeing the danger of
centrality has to be there
it's mutually exclusive yeah so if a
person claims both
that's a contradiction in terms means ah
they're not seeing where real danger is
so that's when they take mindfulness on
their own terms
and then they take the concern behind
the mindfulness on their own terms
so this oh no it is concerned but it's
not because it's in your own terms
as in you took the ownership of it the
concern is exactly that that which you
cannot own
that you are subjected to not other way
around
you wouldn't be drinking the poison if
you inconceivable
so if you think you know you it's
poisonous yet you're still drinking it
means you just took to to to think to
know that what poison is because if it were
that what poison is because if it were
truly
that poison that you're thinking of to
really you wouldn't even touch it
you would that as would have said the
danger would have become apparent
and that would reveal itself to you if
you're self-honest
so you have the faith in the buddha's
instruction yet here you are
contradicting that
but if you were honest you would see
that contradiction and then you would
take that as a symptom
of i'm not seeing this deeply enough
it's exactly what i just said
a few minutes ago like i'm sure many
people would think
oh but i know what dukkha is but i don't
feel like sent extreme
sense of urgency to practice dhamma and
i'm neither going mad
means you don't know what dukkha is
that's what i said because if you were
to know what dukkha is you will be
full on bent on practicing the dharma or
losing your mind
you cannot bear that in itself without
addressing it
you cannot stay with it with the dukkha
in a purest form that needs to be seen
and understood
that's the way i said literally all he
teaches is
suffering and freedom from it nothing
nothing else
everything he ever said
not how to find a way in between a bit
of both
suffering which it's fine if you don't
want to do it
but it's not fine if you claim you're
doing it while you're not doing it
because if you did understand what took
is
you wouldn't it would be the directions
would be automatic
i need to deal with this and if you're
unable to deal with this or if you try
ignoring the fact that you need to deal
with this well the other direction then
it's taken off madness
you will not be able to stay on that
level
so either dealing with it or going mad
or maintain the cover up as you never
really admit what's underneath
because if you do admit what's
underneath your cover up you cannot
forget that
and people who experience anxiety know
that it's back to the poison drink
because you wouldn't be your actions reveal that
you wouldn't be your actions reveal that
you
you are drinking because you're
concerned about yourself already so if you knew
about yourself already so if you knew
that this action was going to hurt you
even worse
you wouldn't be doing it so it's a
contradiction you wouldn't say
yeah poison which can that's what it
would have meant like like when he would
say like you know a man wishing for his
welfare not for his harm
would heed my instruction as in even the
one who doesn't accept his instruction
if he was self-honest he would realize
that it's for his welfare
so even the person who engages with
sensuality and unwholesome behavior deep
down it's always rooted in wanting their own
it's always rooted in wanting their own
welfare and not their own harm
that is the universal principle for
every human being in life in their own
life engaging in sensuality because you
think it's
good for you yeah but if you realize
that it's
you can't both realize that it's bad for
you and engaged
because the reason for engagement is to
not see that it's bad